Guide to the David Edward Cronin Papers 1861-1911 MS 670.9
New-York Historical Society
David E. Cronin papers
1861-1911
New-York Historical Society
Cronin, David Edward, 1839-1925
MS 670.9
4 Linear feet
This collection consists of material relating to and collected by the artist David E. Cronin, Civil War illustrator and member of the 1st N.Y. Mounted Rifles. Material includes memoirs, correspondence, and documents of Cronin and other Civil War soldiers, as well as Cronin's sketches of Civil War subjects, and a number of published volumes hand-illustrated by Cronin. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Access Restrictions
Materials in this collection may be stored offsite. For more information on making arrangements to consult them, please visit www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donation, Daniel Parish, Jr.
"War Relics and Reminiscences: An Appendix to Seth Eyland's Memoirs, by the Author," donated by the Association of Veterans of the First New York Mounted Rifles, 1893.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in five series:
Series I. War Relics and Reminiscences
Series II. Cavalry Album
Series III. Memoirs of W.W. Goldsborough
Series IV. Correspondence
Series V. Illustrated Volumes
Chronology
1839 July 12 David Edward Cronin born, Greenwich, NY.
1855 Cronin moves to New York City after studying art with Alban Conant in Troy, NY. In New York, he works in a law firm, and opens a studio on Canal Street. Cronin becomes a clerk at the Bryan Gallery of Art, where he copies old masters.
[1857-1860] Cronin travels to London and France to study art.
1861-1865 During the Civil War, Cronin serves as Private, Captain, and Brevet Major in the 1st New York Mounted Rifles, a cavalry outfit stationed in eastern Virginia and North Carolina. He also serves as a staff artist for Harper's Weekly under the pseudonym Seth Eyland.
[1865]-1874 Cronin works as a journalist. In 1872, he establishes The Binghamton [N.Y.] Times, which he also edits and publishes until 1874.
1874-[late 1870s] Cronin returns to art in New York City, painting a number of works depicting army life. He also works as a lawyer in New York, then moves to Texas to become a railroad promoter.
[1879] After his railroad venture fails, Cronin returns to New York and begins his life as a professional illustrator.
1880s-1890s Cronin illustrates poems of Poe, Browning, Keats, Shelley, Byron, and Tennyson, as well as Pepys' Diary, General U.S. Grant's Memoirs, Macaulay's Lays of Ancient Rome.
1884 Cronin's autobiography, The Evolution of a Life, described in the Memoirs of Major Seth Eyland is published, containing numerous marginal illustrations. (Seth Eyland was Cronin's pseudonym during the Civil War when he worked as an illustrator for Harper's Weekly.)
[c1887] Cronin meets Daniel Parish, Jr., who becomes his benefactor for nearly twenty-three years. The two cooperate on collecting and illustrating historical works, especially those relating to the Civil War.
1888-1893 He gathers material for an appendix to The Evolution of a Life, including correspondence, muster rolls, commissions, orders, and reports. This collection becomes the five bound volumes entitled War Relics and Reminiscences: An Appendix to Seth Eyland's Memoirs, by the Author.
1890 Cronin moves to Philadelphia, becoming a political cartoonist for the Philadelphia Record from 1892 to 1895.
1893-1902 The artist gathers material for the 'Cavalry Album,' his collection of correspondence, personal narratives, reports, and other items relating to cavalrymen in the Civil War.
1901-1902 Cronin illustrates the memoirs of Major W.W. Goldsborough, Confederate Army.
1902-1903 Cronin illustrates the poems of Joseph Rodman Drake, including The Culprit Fay.
1908-1910 Cronin writes and illustrates The Vest Mansion, its Historical and Romantic Associations as Confederate and Union Headquarters, 1862-1865.
1925 June 9 Cronin dies in Philadelphia.
Related Materials
Material relating to the 1st N.Y. Mounted Rifles can be found in the Regiments collection. The collection War 1861-1865 contains a number of letters written by Cronin. See Manuscript Department card catalog for details.
The Library holds copies of Bibliography Relating to the Works Hand Illustrated by David Edward Cronin; The Evolution of a Life, described in the Memoirs of Major Seth Eyland, and a typewritten copy of Cronin's article "When Union Square Was Away Uptown." It also has a copy of Personal Memoirs of U.S. Grant illustrated by Cronin.
The Library also holds two copies of History of the Fifteenth Pennsylvania Volunteer Cavalry which was Recruited and Known as the Anderson Cavalry in the Rebellion of 1861-1865, the published version of the draft found in Series II.
In addition, the Library has W.W. Goldsborough's The Maryland Line in the Confederate States Army.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of material relating to and collected by the artist David E. Cronin, Civil War illustrator and member of the 1st N.Y. Mounted Rifles. Material includes memoirs, correspondence, and documents of Cronin and other Civil War soldiers, as well as Cronin's sketches of Civil War subjects, and a number of published volumes hand-illustrated by Cronin.
The five-volume War Relics and Reminiscences, compiled by Cronin as an appendix to his published memoirs The Evolution of a Life, consist of illustrations by Cronin, post war-correspondence with veterans, and war-time correspondence, orders, and diary entries. The volumes detail the activities of the 1st N.Y. Mounted Rifles during the Civil War, in Virginia and North Carolina. The collection also contains material collected by Cronin related to Civil War cavalries (formerly titled the "Cavalry Album"), including correspondence, reminscences, portraits, histories, military documents, and newspaper clippings. Also included in the David E. Cronin Papers are the war reminscences of Confederate Major W.W. Goldsborough, one box of correspondence from Cronin, mostly to his patron Daniel Parish Jr., and a number of volumes hand illustrated by Cronin.
The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Harper's weekly; Soldiers -- Conduct of life; Soldiers -- Recreation; Soldiers' writings; Veterans' writings, American -- New York (State).; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Biography.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Cavalry operations.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Medical care.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Personal Narratives.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Portraits.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Regimental histories.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1861-1865.; Correspondence.; Diaries.; Military records.; Photographs.; Portraits.; Sketches.; Budd, Francis, active 1860s; Budd, Samuel, active 1860s; Cronin, David Edward, 1839-1925; Drake, Joseph Rodman, 1795-1820; Goldsborough, W. W. (William Worthington), 1831-1901; Parish, Daniel; Parker, Edwin; Turner, Thomas; Wagner, John; New Jersey. Cavalry; New York (State). Militia. Regiment, 12th; United States. Army. Cavalry, 6th; United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 56th (1861-1865); United States. Army. Pennsylvania Cavalry Regiment, 15th (1862-1865)
- Series I. War Relics and Reminiscences
  Scope and Contents note
  "War Relics and Reminiscences: An Appendix to Seth Eyland's Memoirs, by the Author" are five scrapbook volumes containing illustrations (black & white and color); post-war correspondence; and war-time orders, diary entries (transcriptions of), and correspondence, compiled by Cronin c 1888-1893 as an appendix to his The Evolution of a Life, Described in the Memoirs of Major Seth Eyland. The five scrapbook volumes contain numerous references to the published memoirs. An item-level calendar exists for War Relics and Reminiscences, see Manuscript Department staff.
  The volumes detail the activities of the 1st New York Mounted Rifles during the Civil War, in Virginia along the York and James Rivers, and in North Carolina. This cavalry unit participated in the following campaigns: Deserted House (Jan. 1863), Longstreet's seige of Suffolk (May 1863), Bottom's Bridge (Feb. 1864), Drewry's Bluff or Fort Darlington (May 1864), and The Darbytown Road (Oct. 1864). Material also describes daily routines such as picket duty, orderly and courier duty, and scouting patrols on the Peninsula. Some skirmishes with Confederate bushwhackers and the looting activities of the Mounted Rifles are also described.
  War Relics and Reminiscences contain four large collections of war-time correspondence from soldiers to their friends and family, which detail camp life, field duties, recreation, diet, medical care, desertions and prisoners, bounties and enlistments, politics, slavery, and skirmishes. These collections are the Samuel and Francis Budd Letters, the Edwin Parker Letters, the Thomas Turner Letters, and the John Wagner Letters. See calendar for locations and indexes for these collections.
  Material in the five volumes is arranged alphabetically by commissioned officers, then alphabetically by non-commissioned officers and soldiers.
  - War Relics and Reminiscences, 1861-1892 (Volume I)
  - War Relics and Reminiscences, 1861-1892 (Volume II)
  - War Relics and Reminiscences, 1861-1892 (Volume III)
  - War Relics and Reminiscences, 1861-1892 (Volume IV)
  - War Relics and Reminiscences, 1861-1892 (Volume V)
- Series II. Cavalry Album
  This series contains mostly items related to Civil War cavalry units collected by Cronin, then inlaid and bound together as the "Cavalry Album." The pages were, at some point, disbound and foldered. The folder level arrangement of the album has been retained, though the original order of the items within the volume is unclear.
  Some material in the Cavalry Album is arranged alphabetically by soldier, and includes correspondence, reminiscences, addresses, military documents, and published items. See container list for names. Cronin's folder contains a portrait and military documents. Some post-war correspondence (both Union and Confederate) has been filed separately.
  Further material relating to soldiers, mostly portraits, is arranged by cavalry. Units from New York, Pennsylvania, and New Jersey are represented, as well as U.S. Cavalry. In addition, the Cavalry Album contains several portraits of army nurses, images of army camps, inventory reports, muster rolls, dispatches, orders, and newspaper clippings, especially those related to the assassination of Abraham Lincoln.
  This series also contains an incomplete draft manuscript of the "History of the Fifteenth Pennsylvania Cavalry."
  - Balmer, B.F. "My Escape from Andersonville", 1904, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Barnett, G.A. Letters from Camp Butler, Newport News, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Cronin, David E., 1861-1906 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Dean, William Orders (bulk), 1858-1868 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Hunterson, John C. Includes address at Gettysburg (1890), 1890, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Kleinz, Christian Military documents, 1863-1866 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lyon, Arthur P. Article about Lyon, 15th Penn., 1905 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - McMullan, Joseph A. Letters, 1862 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Murray, George Letters to Cronin, 1861-1862 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Pauli, Henry A., 1862-1864, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Platt, George C. Reminiscences, portrait, 1899, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Richardson, G.W. Passes, 1862-1863 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Smith, Edwin J. Portrait, reminiscences, scattered wartime diary pages, 1861-1864, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Spang, William "Search for Jefferson Davis and the capture of General Braxton Bragg", 1865, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Speese, A.J. Letters, address given at Gettysburg (1901), 1895-1901 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Strang, E.B. Sunshine and Shadows of the Late Civil War (1898), 1898, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Tailof, [Iban] Letters to Cronin, 1861-1862 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Thomas, Hampton S. "Some Personal Reminscences of Service in the Cavalry of the Army of the Potomac", 1889 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Uber, George W. Letters to Cronin, portrait, 1899 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Wilkeson Letters to Cronin, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - War-time correspondence, Misc., 1861-1865, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Post-war Correspondence and Reminiscences, 1892-1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Post-war Correspondence and Reminscences, 1892-1905, undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Confederate Post-war Correspondence, 1901 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "History of the Fifteenth Pennsylvania Cavalry"--p. 2-98, [1905] (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - "History of the Fifteenth Pennsylvania Cavalry"--p. 100-200, [1905] (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "History of the Fifteenth Pennsylvania Cavalry"--p. 206-300, [1905] (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - "History of the Fifteenth Pennsylvania Cavalry"--p. 301-399, [1905] (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - "History of the Fifteenth Pennsylvania Cavalry"--p. 400-499, [1905] (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - "History of the Fifteenth Pennsylvania Cavalry"--p. 500-599, [1905] (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - "History of the Fifteenth Pennsylvania Cavalry"--p. 600-700, [1905] (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 15th Pennsylvania Cavalry--Reminiscences, 1904 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 15th Pennsylvania Cavalry--Reminscences, [1904] (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1st N.Y. Mounted Rifles--Portraits, 1890, undated (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 10th N.Y. Cavalry--Portraits, Proceedings of 36th Reunion, 1890, 1897, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - 1st, 2nd, 3rd, 4th Pennsylvania Cavalry--Portraits, 1890, 1898, undated (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - 3rd Pennsylvania Cavalry--"Constitution and By-Laws of Company H, Third Pennsylvania Cavalry with A Brief History and Muster Roll." Annotated by A.J. Speese, 1907 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 5th Pennsylvania Cavalry--Portraits, Undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - 5th Pennsylvania Cavalry--Portraits (by company), 1895, undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - 6th, 8th, 11th, 13th, 15th, 20th Pennyslvania Cavalry--Portraits, Undated (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 6th U.S. Cavalry--History, Undated (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Cavalry--Portraits, Undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - N.J. Cavalry--Portraits, Undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Regiments--Portraits, Undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Confederates--Portraits, Undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Portraits--Misc., 1899, undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Photographic Portraits--Misc., Undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Nurses--Portraits (bulk), 1905, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Camp Scenes--Photographs, 1864-1866 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - Camp Scenes, 1861-1865 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Inventory Reports and Muster Rolls, 1864-1866 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - Dispatches, 1863 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Orders, 1862-1865 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1882-1900, undated (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Clippings--Assassination of Abraham Lincoln, 1896, 1902, undated (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Map--Capt. Wallen's Exploration, 1859 (Or, Ut, Id) (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Misc. Items, 1863-1907 (Box 13, Folder 3)
- Series III. Memoirs of W.W. Goldsborough
  This series contains handwritten memoirs entitled "War Reminiscences" by Major W.W. [William Worthington] Goldsborough of the Confederate Army, 2nd Maryland Infantry. The original pages have been inlaid, and Goldsborough added to his narrative in the margins of the oversized pages, often creating two separate narratives on one page.
  Goldsborough's memoirs discuss John Brown's raid, an aborted trip to Baltimore by Lincoln, unrest in Baltimore at the start of the war, Confederate army camp life, activities in MD and VA, truce meetings, and the battle of Gettysburg.
  Also included are numerous newspaper clippings of Civil War reminiscences written by Goldsborough for the Philadelphia Record [1899-1900], which detail his experiences in 2nd Bull Run, Malvern, Antietam, Gettysburg, and Harper's Ferry, as well as his capture and life as a prisoner at Fort Delaware, Fort Pulaski, and Morris Island. The articles are mounted and annotated by Goldsborough.
  This series also contains portraits of Goldsborough, both sketches and photographs, a photograph of a 2nd Maryland Infantry C.S.A. memorial, and several obituaries of Goldsborough.
  - W.W. Goldsborough, [1901] (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - W.W. Goldsborough, [1901] (Box 14, Folder 2)
- Series IV. Correspondence
  The bulk of correspondence is letters from Cronin to his patron and friend, Daniel Parish, Jr., 1887-1909. Letters discuss Cronin's work on Evolution of a Life, the Cavalry Album, The Culprit Fay, his bibliography, Goldsborough's memoirs, and other endeavors, sometimes detailing the lives of particular personages found in his works and reminiscing about his service in the Civil War. A number of letters deal with his relationship with Parish, illuminating aspects of their occasionally contentious patron-artist relationship, especially financial ones. Cronin also muses on the life of the artist in his correspondence.
  Letters to Parish also cover a 1901 journey by Cronin to Virginia, which include observations on the South and racial issues. In addition, a number of letters mention The New-York Historical Society, and its new building on Central Park West.
  This series also contains one folder of correspondence to Cronin from others regarding his work, as well as a few letters from Cronin to others, including one to his sister written from Virginia in August, 1865, and a few letters between others.
  Also included is a number of postcards and photos, mostly of Williamsburg, Va. and some notes of Cronin's (sent to Parish) entitled "Phila. May 13th 1897 Notes of a conversation held between F.A. Whitehead (Lincoln, Del.) And D.E. Cronin at the Reading Terminal Station, between trains, yesterday, May 12th. Submitted to Mr. Parish for his information and guidance in the matter of the regimental history, while reminding him that my motives are personal vindication and self defense."
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1887-1889 (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1890-1891 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1892-1895 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1896-1900 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1901 (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1902 Jan.-June (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1902 July-Dec. (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1903 (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1904 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1905 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1906 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1907 (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Letters to Daniel Parish, Jr., 1909 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - Other Correspondence, 1865, 1881-1909, 1911, undated (Box 15, Folder 14)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes a letter to Cronin from Harry E. Widener, Land Title Building, Philadelphia, 1911 July 10.
    Immediate source of acquisition: Gift of Edward C. Peple Jr., 2018 (accession no. MS-2018-011).
  - Correspondence--fragments, Undated (Box 15, Folder 15)
  - Notes (sent to Parish), 1897 (Box 15, Folder 16)
  - Postcards and Photographs, 1910, undated (Box 15, Folder 17)
- Series V. Illustrated Volumes
  This series contains volumes illustrated by Cronin, including two copies of Joseph Rodman Drakes's poem The Culprit Fay, a copy of a limited edition Bibliography Relating to the Works Hand Illustrated by David Edward Cronin, and The Vest Mansion: Its Historical and Romantic Associations As Confederate and Union Headquarters, 1862-1865, written and illustrated by Cronin.
  - Cronin's illustrations for The Culprit Fay, by Joseph Rodman Drake (1902 edition), 1902, undated (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Unbound; with a manuscript copy of poem.
  - The Culprit Fay, by Joseph Rodman Drake (1835 edition), illustrated by Cronin, 1835, undated (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - Bibliography Relating to the Works Hand Illustrated by David Edward Cronin, 1903 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    Illustrated by Cronin.
  - Illustrated title page for Vol. 6 of The Evolution of a Life, Undated (Box 16, Folder 4)
    Loose page titled "Chapter XXII."
  - The Vest Mansion: Its Historical and Romantic Associations As Confederate and Union Headquarters, 1862-1865, 1908-1910 (Box 17)
    By Cronin; unbound.
  - The Evolution of a Life, Described in the Memoirs of Major Seth Eyland, 1884 (published) (Volume [copy 1])
    Cronin's autobiography, hand illustrated.
  - The Evolution of a Life, Described in the Memoirs of Major Seth Eyland, 1884 (published) (Volume [copy 2])
  - The Evolution of a Life, Described in the Memoirs of Major Seth Eyland, 1884 (published) (Volume [copy 3])
    Immediate source of acquisition: This copy the gift of Edward C. Peple Jr., 2018 (accession no. MS-2018-011).
  - The Daughters of King Lear, Undated (Box 18)
    Framed triptych engraving, with watercolor and pencil tinting, of "The Daughters of King Lear," left to right: "Goneril," "Cordelia," and "Regan."
- N-YHS Exhibit Labels
  Labels for an exhibit of Cronin's work, possibly Jan.-Mar., 1941
  - N-YHS Exhibit Labels, Undated (Box 13, Folder 4)